Guide to the Rebecca West Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Rebecca West collection
1913-1996
GEN MSS 239
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.75
(9 boxes) + 2 cases
The collection contains letters to and from West, including extensive correspondences with Emanie Sachs Arling and Doris Stevens, as well as letters from Norman Mackenzie, Sara Tugander Melville, Jonathan Mitchell, Harold F. Rubinstein, and Reginald Turner; miscellaneous writings by West; and correspondence and memorabilia of West assembled by Gordon S. Haight.
West, Rebecca, 1892-1983
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This listing encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts pertaining to Rebecca West acquired by gift and purchase from various sources by the Beinecke Library from 1960 to the present. Provenance has been noted briefly on the inital folder of each accession; for further information, see the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Papers in Box 11 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Associated Materials
For the papers donated by Rebecca West to Yale University in 1959, see GEN MSS 105, Rebecca West Papers; for related West material, see GEN MSS 240, G. Evelyn Hutchinson Papers Relating to Rebecca West.
REBECCA WEST 1892-1983
Rebecca West is the pseudonym of Cicely Isabel Fairfield, British journalist and novelist. Her major works include Black Lamb and Grey Falcon (1942), a study of Yugoslavia; A Train of Powder (1955), reports on the Nuremberg Trials; and The Meaning of Treason (1949), on the trial of William Joyce, who broadcast for Nazi Germany as Lord Haw-Haw. Among her novels are The Return of the Soldier (1918), The Fountain Overflows (1957), and The Birds Fall Down (1966). She was created Dame of the British Empire in 1959.
West's decade-long relationship with H. G. Wells produced one son, Anthony Panther West, born in 1914. In 1930 West married the banker Henry Andrews, who died in 1968.
For further information consult the Dictionary of National Biography.
Scope and Contents
The Rebecca West Collection spans the dates 1913-1984 and is organized in four series. Series I, Correspondence, consists of letters to and from Rebecca West and is alphabetically arranged by name of correspondent. Series II, Writings, is organized in three subseries: Books, Articles, and Writings of Others. Series III, Rebecca West Papers of Gordon S. Haight, is organized in three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers. Materials acquired since September 1996 are located in Series IV, Additions since September 1996, and are listed in accession order.
Series I, Correspondence, contains mainly letters by West herself, in some cases donated by their recipients at West's request. Correspondents include Romney Brent, Henry James Forman, A. S. Frere, Lady Elizabeth Iddesleigh, Norman Mackenzie, C. K. Ogden, and Reginald Turner. West's letters to Sara Tugander Melville describe her daily life during the period following the birth of Anthony West and her travels to Italy and America during the 1920s. West's correspondence with Gregg T. Sinclair, begun when Sinclair sent her a fan letter about The Judge, documents her interest in visiting the Sinclairs in Japan and later in America.
The two extensive correspondences in the collection are those of Emanie Sachs Arling and Doris Stevens, both of whom West met during her first American lecture tour in 1923-24. West's letters to both women contain much information about her personal life, such as her health, her travels, life at Ibstone House with Henry Andrews, and her relations with family members. West's view of the troubled relationship between her and her son Anthony is particularly well documented, including her reaction to the publication of Heritage and to Anthony's divorce from his first wife and relocation to America. In addition, the correspondence with Stevens reflects West's involvement in the controversies surrounding Joseph McCarthy and the American anti-Communist movement.
Series II, Writings, is divided into three subseries: Books, Articles, and Writings of Others. Books includes corrected galleys for The Birds Fall Down and The Thinking Reed, while Articles contains documentation of West's famous series "Behind the Witch-Hunts," including typescripts, clippings, and letters to the editor of the London Times concerning the series. Folder 172 contains clippings of articles by and about West's American lecture tour that appeared in the Japan Advertiser.
Series III, Rebecca West Papers of Gordon Haight, contains correspondence from West and Henry Andrews to Haight, who was a member of the Department of English at Yale during West's visits to the university. There are also a typescript photocopy of Haight's response to Anthony West's portrait of West in Aspects of a Life, newspaper clippings, photographs, and other memorabilia.
Series IV, Additions Since September 1996, contains recent acquisitions arranged in accession order.
Oversize contains two items from Series II. Box 11, Restricted Fragile Papers, contains fragile originals from Series I-III.
Authors, English -- 20th Century -- Archives; English literature -- 20th Century; Women authors; Haight, Gordon Sherman; MacKenzie, Norman, 1921-2013; Melville, Sara Tugander; Mitchell, Jonathan; Rubinstein, Harold; Sachs, Emanie N.; Stevens, Doris; Turner, Reggie, 1869?-1938; West, Rebecca, 1892-1983
- Correspondence, 1912-81; Series I; 1.25; (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, contains
  alphabetically arranged correspondence.
  - Adcock, Mr., [1922?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aiken, Zoey, 1925 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anglin, Margaret, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arling, Emanie, 1936-64 (Box 1, Folder 4-31)
    Includes ALS from Henry Andrews,
    1963
  - Arling, Emanie, 1965-76, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 32-36)
  - Austin, F. Britten, [1936] (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Barker, A. L. (Audrey Lillian), 1967-81 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Bay, Mrs., 1959 Mar 7 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Brent, Romney, 1934-70, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Bryant, Arthur, Sir, 1959 Oct 29 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Bullett, Gerald, 1930 Dec 11 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Christy, Mr., 1928 Jun (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Colchester, Mayor of, 1959 Jun 11 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Dawson Scott, C. A. (Catherine Amy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Findlater, Richard, 1982 Feb 22 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Forman, Henry James, [1919]-24 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Frere, A. S., 1934-58, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Frere, Pat, 1934-46, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Garland, Madge, 1976-81, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Gaunt, William, 1965 Jan 15 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Goodwin, Miss, [1918?] May 4 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Greacen, [Robert], 1981 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Grierson, Herbert John Clifford, Sir, 1935 Jun 4 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - [Gunther?], John, 1954 Feb 22 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Hammerton, H. C., 1980 Jan 19 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - [Hastings, Macdonald], [1948?] (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Iddesleigh, Henry Stafford, Lord, [n.y.] Oct 13 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Iddesleigh, Elizabeth Lowndes Stafford, Lady, [1952-74] (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Kennedy, Daisy, [1937 Mar] (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Knopf, Blanche, [1926 Nov] (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Liebert, Herman W., 1968 Nov 25 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Lowndes, Marie Belloc, 1927-46, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Mackenzie, Norman, 1972-82 (Box 2, Folder 64-65)
  - Marques, Susan Lowndes, 1947-71 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Melville, S. T. (Sara Tugander), 1912-36, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 67-72)
  - Mitchell, Jonathan, 1938-77 (Box 2, Folder 73-75)
  - Morris, John, 1943-74, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 76-79)
  - Ogden, C. K., 1917-24, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Pinker, James, [1917-24], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Robison, Robert, 1944-81 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    Includes 2 letters signed by
    Diana Stainforth
  - Rubinstein, Harold F., 1912-18, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 83-87)
    Photograph of Rebecca West enclosed
    in letter of 1912 Aug 23
  - Russell, Leonard, 1944-67 (Box 3, Folder 88-89)
  - Russell, Elizabeth Dilys
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Russell, Leonard, Box 3, folder 88
  - Seldes, Gilbert, [1924]-65, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Senhouse, Roger, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Sinclair, Gregg M., 1924-73, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 92-95)
  - Simpson, John L., 1968-75 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    Includes letter from Simpson to
    Polly (Laura K.) Lada-Mocarski
  - Smith, Adrian, 1978 May 16 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Spooner, Reginald, 1948 Oct 18 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    Newspaper clippings enclosed
  - Stanhope, Mrs., 1970 Apr 13 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Stevens, Doris, 1922-59 (Box 3, Folder 100-115)
  - Stevens, Doris, 1960-62, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 116-121)
  - Stokes, Sewell, 1924 Oct 30 (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Streatfield, Miss, 1943 Aug 5 (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - Turner, Reginald, 1921-35 (Box 4, Folder 124-126)
    Includes letter to Turner from
    James Agate
  - Van Thal, Herbert, 1941-68, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Watson, Vera, 1957-81 (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - [Wedgwood, C.] Veronica, 1948, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - "Howard and Mary" (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - Unidentified; [from Porlock], 1922 (Box 4, Folder 131)
- Writings, 1913-67; Series II; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  Series II, Writings, is organized into three
  subseries. Books and Articles are arranged
  alphabetically by title. Writings of Others
  is arranged alphabetically by name of author.
  - BOOKS
    - The Birds Fall Down
      - Typescript carbon, corrected, [1966] (Box 5, Folder 132-148)
      - Galley proofs, corrected, 1966
        See: Oversize, Box 8, folder 191
    - The New Meaning of Treason
      - Photocopy of setting typescript, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 149-152)
      - Photocopy of setting typescript, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 153-159)
    - The Thinking Reed
      - Galleys, annotated, 1936
        See: Oversize, Box 9, folder 192
  - ARTICLES
    - "Aspects of Love and Mutual Dislike"
      - Clipping, [1963] (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - "Behind the Witch-Hunts"
      - Typescripts and typescripts carbon, corrected, [1953] (Box 6, Folder 161-164)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 165)
      - "Memorandum on McCarthyism"
        - Typescript carbon, [1953] (Box 6, Folder 166)
      - Letters to the Editor of the Times concerning the article, 1953 Mar-May (Box 6, Folder 167)
      - "Miss West Files an Answer"
        - Newspaper clipping from the New York Herald-Tribune, 1953 Jun 22 (Box 6, Folder 168)
    - "Elegy"
      - Typescript corrected, signed, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 169)
    - "Elizabeth Montagu"
      - Autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 170)
      - Galley proof, corrected, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 171)
    - Japan Advertiser series on America
      - Newspaper clippings, 1924-25 (Box 6, Folder 172)
    - "My Favorite Poem"
      - Autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 173)
    - "My Religion"
      - Newspaper clipping, 1925 Sep 10 (Box 6, Folder 174)
    - "On His Way to the Bank"
      - Newspaper clipping, 1967 Nov 12 (Box 6, Folder 175)
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Okakura-Kakuso: The White Fox
      - Typescript carbon, inscribed "To Gregg and Marjorie Sinclair, Henry M. Andrews, Rebecca West...July 1, 1956.", 1913 Mar (Box 6, Folder 176)
      - Clippings about Rebecca West, 1925-68, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 177)
- Rebecca West Papers of Gordon Haight, 1962-83; Series III; 0.4; (1 box)
  Series III, Rebecca West Papers of Gordon Haight, is organized into three subseries.
  Correspondence is divided into Rebecca West
  Correspondence, Henry Andrews Correspondence,
  and G. Evelyn Hutchinson Correspondence. Each
  is chronologically arranged. Writings and Other
  Papers are arranged alphabetically by title or
  type of material.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Rebecca West Correspondence, 1962-83 (Box 7, Folder 178-180)
    - Henry Andrews Correspondence, 1966, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 181)
    - G. Evelyn Hutchinson Correspondence, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 182)
  - WRITINGS
    - "Mr. West's Vendetta": drafts, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 183)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Memorial service order, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 184)
    - Newspaper clippings about West, 1972-83 (Box 7, Folder 185-187)
    - Photograph and slides of West and Henry Andrews, 1967-82 (Box 7, Folder 188-189)
    - Place cards for the publication dinner for H. G. Wells and Rebecca West by Gordon N. Ray, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 190)
- Oversize, 1936-66; 2; (2 cases)
  Oversize contains two items from Series II.
  - The Birds Fall Down
    - Galley proofs, corrected, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 191)
  - The Thinking Reed
    - Galley proofs, corrected, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 192)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.25; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 12 (Box 10, Folder 193)
  - Box 2, folder 40 (Box 10, Folder 194)
  - Box 2, folder 63 (Box 10, Folder 195)
  - Box 2, folder 68 (Box 10, Folder 196)
  - Box 2, folder 69 (Box 10, Folder 197)
  - Box 2, folder 70 (Box 10, Folder 198)
  - Box 2, folder 71 (Box 10, Folder 199)
  - Box 2, folder 72 (Box 10, Folder 200)
  - Box 2, folder 73 (Box 10, Folder 201)
  - Box 2, folder 81 (Box 10, Folder 202)
  - Box 3, folder 98 (Box 10, Folder 203)
  - Box 3, folder 100 (Box 10, Folder 204)
  - Box 3, folder 112 (Box 10, Folder 205)
  - Box 3, folder 114 (Box 10, Folder 206)
  - Box 3, folder 115 (Box 10, Folder 207)
  - Box 3, folder 117 (Box 10, Folder 208)
  - Box 3, folder 118 (Box 10, Folder 209)
  - Box 3, folder 125 (Box 10, Folder 210)
  - Box 3, folder 133 (Box 10, Folder 211)
  - Box 5, folder 148 (Box 10, Folder 212)
  - Box 5, folder 149 (Box 10, Folder 213)
  - Box 6, folder 165 (Box 10, Folder 214)
- Additions Since September 1996, 1961 Jul 30; Series IV
  - Letter to Mrs. [Eleanor] Nudd: Ibstone House, Nr. High Wycombe, Bucks., 1961 Jul 30 (Box 11, Folder 215)
    1 item (2 pages); 20 cm.
    ALS.
    With: envelope.
    Given in 1996.
  - Letter to Mr. Smart: 48 Kingston House North [London], 1975 Dec 5 (Box 11, Folder 216)
    Purchased in 1998.
    Acc: 980113-c
  - Letter to Beatrice [Kaufman]: Ibstone House, 1943 Feb 1 (Box 11, Folder 217)
    1 item (2 pages): 25 cm.
    Acc: 980211-c
  - Correspondence and contracts with Arnold Weissberger concerning the rights to "The Birds Fall Down", 1959-74, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 218-19)
    23 items.
    Acc: 980211-d
  - Letters: various places, to [Doctor] Bethel Solomon, 1975-78, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 220)
    7 items.
    4 ALS, 1 APcS and 2 TLS discussing
    West's health, personal news, and
    her reaction to Anthony West's
    Mortal Wounds and George Painter's
    biography of Proust.
    With: holograph manuscript of notes
    on sightseeing possibilities in
    Mexico (written for Solomon).
    Gift, 1999.
    Acc: 990512-a
  - Letters: various places, to Charles Curran, 1947-49, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 221)
    10 items.
    8 TLS and 2 ALS mainly discussing
    her political views, particularly
    on John Amery, William Joyce, and
    the English and American Communist
    Parties. An undated TLS offers her
    highly negative opinion of the
    "solemn dirt" of A Streetcar Named Desire. Purchase, 1999.
    Acc.: 19991109-a
  - Letter: Ibstone House, to Edward H. Pearson, 1946 Jan 18 (Box 11, Folder 222)
    1 item (2 L.); 21 cm.
    TLS containing biographical
    information, including West's comments
    on her parents, and discussion of
    "War Brides" article.
    Purchase, 2000.
    Acc.: 20000317-r
  - Letter: Ibstone House, to Fanny C. Goldstein, 1956 Sep 5 (Box 11, Folder 223)
    1 item (1 L.); 18 cm.
    ALS responding angrily to
    Goldstein's "cruel and insolent"
    letter and defending herself
    forcefully against the charge
    of anti-Semitism in "two books
    of mine....Please read nothing else
    of mine."
    Acc.: 20000727-r
  - Letter: Ibstone House, to Lewis Mumford, 1968 Aug 6 (Box 11, Folder 224)
    1 item (1 L.); 30 cm.
    TLS commenting on an article by
    Mumford in the 1968 Jul 6 New Yorker. West talks about the
    changing usage of footpaths,
    her love of walking and the country,
    and the relocation of tradesmen
    from London to "country places."
    Salutation reads: "Dear Mr. Muford."
    Acc.: 20000727-s
  - Photograph: Alex. Ayton, 42 and 43 Bruntsfield Place, Edinburgh, [ca. 1912-13] (Box 11, Folder 225)
    1 item.
    Class portrait of class at George
    Watson's Ladies' Seminary, George
    Square. Cicely Fairfield in top
    row, third from left.
    C. G. MacDonald in third row,
    sixth from left.
    Accompanied by: clipping,
    1996 Apr 15.
    Gift, 1997.
    Acc: 19970226-c
  - Letter: 15, Orchard Court, Portman Square, W.1 [London], to [Betty] Ross, 1931 Nov 12 (Box 11, Folder 226)
    1 item (1 L.); 20 cm.
    TLS inviting her for a visit and
    mentioning photographs.
    Purchase, 2001.
    Acc: 20010723-a
  - Letter: 15, Orchard Court, Portman Square, W.1 [London], to A. P. Herbert, 1933 Oct 11 (Box 11, Folder 227)
    TLS complimenting Herbert on an
    article exposing coroners.
    Purchase, 2003.
    Acc: 20030114-q
  - Letter: 48 Kingston House North, to Mr. Dosse, n.y. Aug 25 (Box 11, Folder 228)
    ALS declining offer of "Huxley book"
    due to eye trouble.
    Acc: 20030812-ah